<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A disputation betwixt the Devill and the Pope. Being a briefe dialogue between Urbanus, 5. Pope of Rome, and Pluto prince of Hell. Concerning the estate of five kingdomes, Spaine, England, France, Ireland. and Scotland. Written by the author to content his friend, being pleasant and delightfull to the reader.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 9 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 4 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A81550</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D1676</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E132_8</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R19486</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99860682</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99860682</idno>
            <idno type="VID">156357</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A81550)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 156357)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 23:E132[8])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A disputation betwixt the Devill and the Pope. Being a briefe dialogue between Urbanus, 5. Pope of Rome, and Pluto prince of Hell. Concerning the estate of five kingdomes, Spaine, England, France, Ireland. and Scotland. Written by the author to content his friend, being pleasant and delightfull to the reader.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1642.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴.</note>
                  <note>A satire in verse.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Urban, --  Pope, 1568-1644.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  Humor --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>royal English blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
                  <q>HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE</q>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:156357:1"/>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:156357:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Diſputation betwixt the DEVILL And the POPE.</p>
            <p>Being a briefe Dialogue between <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rbanus,</hi> 5. Pope of <hi>Rome,</hi> and <hi>Pluto</hi> Prince of Hell.</p>
            <p>Concerning the Eſtate of five Kingdomes, <hi>Spaine, England, France, Ireland.</hi> and <hi>Scotland</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Written by the Author to content his Friend, being Pleaſant and delightfull to the READER.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed, 1642.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="dialogue">
            <pb facs="tcp:156357:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:156357:2"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Devill and the Pope.</speaker>
               <l>THE <hi>Pope</hi> whoſe papall Power all <hi>Roome</hi> controwles</l>
               <l>Wanting more wealth (purchaz'd at price of Soules)</l>
               <l>Fearing the People in each ſeverall Region</l>
               <l>Contemne his Maſſe, and follow true Religion</l>
               <l>Growes much diſtempered; Sicknes doth weigh downe</l>
               <l>His holy head, more then his Triple Crowne</l>
               <l>'Cauſe a report of late is newly riſen</l>
               <l>Some of his Tribe in England are in Priſon</l>
               <l>And many more which did this Land deflower</l>
               <l>Are fled and baniſh'd by the Almighties Power</l>
               <l>Griveing his ſocerie no more bewitches</l>
               <l>By ſpells he raiſeth <hi>Pluto (God of Ritches)</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Well may the People be in mickle danger</l>
               <l>When <hi>Roomes</hi> great <hi>Vicar</hi> doth begin to conjure</l>
               <l>But now the divell's rai'd the <hi>Pope</hi> requires</l>
               <l>New councell from the God of quenchleſſe fires</l>
               <l>It riſes like a <hi>Fryar,</hi> with a hood on't</l>
               <l>To ſhreive the <hi>Pope,</hi> the <hi>Devill</hi> give him good on't</l>
               <l>If their diſcourſe can your attention winne</l>
               <l>Lend us your eare and heare the <hi>Devill</hi> begin.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Devill.</speaker>
               <l>Hayle to your <hi>Holineſſe</hi> what iſ't offends.</l>
               <l>Your King-commanding Power? are your vow'd friends</l>
               <l>Turn'd Traytors to your Crowne, doth <hi>France</hi> deny</l>
               <l>To pay your Annuall tribute? ſtraite I'le fly</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:156357:3"/>
               <l>With Troopes of factious Spirits, ſuch as ſhall</l>
               <l>Con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ert the Rebels; or confound them all:</l>
               <l>If it be <hi>Spaine</hi> Perplexeth you, Ile ſtraite</l>
               <l>With a worſe Plague then that in 88.</l>
               <l>Vex my ambitious <hi>Don</hi> torment him more</l>
               <l>Then did the <hi>Dutch</hi> man, on the Engliſh ſhore;</l>
               <l>After much warre, deepe wounds and many knocks</l>
               <l>Ile give his Country to the Butter box.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pope.</speaker>
               <l>Great <hi>Pluto</hi> (Partner in my See of <hi>Rome</hi>)</l>
               <l>'Tis not for theſe my skill calls thee to come</l>
               <l>Not many dayes (before this time) hath paſt</l>
               <l>Since by my potent charmes I raysd thee laſt</l>
               <l>And bid thee muſter ſpirits (ſuch as are</l>
               <l>Powerfull in ſowing of a civill warre)</l>
               <l>To ſend them into <hi>Ireland</hi> to poſſeſſe</l>
               <l>The Catholicks with their owne wretchedneſſe</l>
               <l>How many yeares in thraldome they did pant</l>
               <l>Vnder the Scepter of the Proteſtant,</l>
               <l>And that by rayſing factions they ſhall ſee</l>
               <l>Their peace agen and former Liberty</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Devill.</speaker>
               <l>This we have done my chiefeſt Spirit error</l>
               <l>The Prince of faction hath rayſ'd up ſuch terror</l>
               <l>In <hi>Iriſh</hi> hearts that rather then they'le yeeld</l>
               <l>They'le waſh with human bloud the fertill field</l>
               <l>And through the generall Kingdome there are none</l>
               <l>But cry or elſe have cauſe to cry O hone.</l>
               <l>Their onſet did beginn tragick and black</l>
               <l>The Engliſh Proteſtant went firſt to wrack.</l>
               <l>Women they killd, young infants they did ſmother</l>
               <l>As if each man forgot he had a mother.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:156357:3"/>
               <l>Brave worke for me, for though I prompt them to it</l>
               <l>They had almoſt as good be dambd as do it</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pope.</speaker>
               <l>But in theſe Spoyles ſhan't I a ſharer bee.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Devill.</speaker>
               <l>Oh yes my Lord when you are damnd like me</l>
               <l>But whilſt this fleſhy ſubſtance thus controwles</l>
               <l>Your Spirit, you can have no ſhare in ſoules</l>
               <l>But when the happy time comes you ſhall dye</l>
               <l>Thou ſhalt be made as great a devill as I</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pope.</speaker>
               <l>Thy happy promiſes doe much reſtore me</l>
               <l>For which I'le ſend as many ſoules before me</l>
               <l>As ſhall enrich thy Kindome but goe on</l>
               <l>Vpon thy <hi>Iriſh</hi> Declaration</l>
               <l>I long to hear't.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Devill.</speaker>
               <l>You ſhall, the <hi>Iriſh</hi> firſt</l>
               <l>Were Conquerors but now they have the worſt</l>
               <l>The valliant Engliſh now the victors be</l>
               <l>And chaſe the bloudy Iriſh Crom a Cree</l>
               <l>From bogg to bogg at every turne they winde them</l>
               <l>and fly as if the <hi>Devill</hi> were behind them</l>
               <l>The amazing miſſery doth ſo beſot them</l>
               <l>They are affraid S. <hi>Patrick</hi> hath forgot them</l>
               <l>The God the Engliſh ſerve doth ſo diſtract them</l>
               <l>Their Beads nor holy water can't protect them</l>
               <l>that now the Proverb ends as it began</l>
               <l>'tis thought a fart will fright an Iriſh man</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pope.</speaker>
               <l>This is diſtaſtefull newes but canſt thou tell</l>
               <l>What factious Spirits doe in England dwell.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:156357:4"/>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Devill.</speaker>
               <l>Few of your Party they are gone as wide</l>
               <l>As moſt report and mad on tother ſide</l>
               <l>There all your Bookes and Beads are counted toyes</l>
               <l>Altars and Tapers are pulld downe by boyes</l>
               <l>Diſcord they ſay doth ſo poſſeſſe the Land</l>
               <l>'Tis thought they will not let the <hi>Organs</hi> ſtand</l>
               <l>The cleane waſh't Surples which our Prieſts put on</l>
               <l>There is the ſmock ot'h Whore of <hi>Babilon</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And I have had report by thoſe have ſeene them</l>
               <l>They breake the windowes cauſe the Saints are in them</l>
               <l>There Pope you muſt expect a certaine loſſe</l>
               <l>A Taylor muſt not ſit with leggs on croſſe</l>
               <l>But ſtrait hee's ſet by'th heeles, (it is a ſigne</l>
               <l>Of Ceremony only not Divine)</l>
               <l>The great grand Biſhop there your Popeſhips cozen</l>
               <l>Is in the Tower, thers 13. to the dozen</l>
               <l>I wonder by what Spirit they are led</l>
               <l>They ſent a man to me without a head</l>
               <l>The tother day but therein they did well</l>
               <l>For were it on 'tis thought 'twould trouble Hell</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Cum Privilegio's</hi> out of date, they cry</l>
               <l>In every ſtreete what new Booke will you buy</l>
               <l>Come buy a booke oth Biſhop of Canterbury</l>
               <l>And with his miſſery they make them merry</l>
               <l>Miters are baniſh't, and ſome hope to ſee</l>
               <l>4. Corner'd Caps will now be brought to 3.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pope.</speaker>
               <l>Prethe no more this newes doth quite diſtract me</l>
               <l>And I ſhall ſowne unleſſe thy helpe protect me</l>
               <l>There is no hope that Nation is farr gone</l>
               <l>Whom neither <hi>Pope</hi> nor <hi>Devill</hi> can worke upon.</l>
            </sp>
            <pb facs="tcp:156357:4"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Devill.</speaker>
               <l>They are diſtracted? to) brother gainſt Brother,</l>
               <l>Friend againſt Friend one Neighbour againſt another</l>
               <l>But this will not laſt long; they are happy men</l>
               <l>And ſoone tis thought will ſettle Peace agen</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pope.</speaker>
               <l>Why then let's give them over let us ſave</l>
               <l>Free from their Power thoſe Catholicks we have</l>
               <l>There is no hopes in <hi>Scotland,</hi> there they be</l>
               <l>Confirm'd too ſure in a fraternity</l>
               <l>Therefore at this time leave me.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pluto.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Pope farewell.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pope.</speaker>
               <l>I to my Chamber goe.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pluto.</speaker>
               <l>And I to Hell.</l>
               <l>Y'haue heard their diſputation and may ſee</l>
               <l>How much to us the Pope's an Enemie</l>
               <l>The <hi>Devill</hi> to; tis likely that we ſhall</l>
               <l>Be happy if wee ſeeke not our owne fall:</l>
               <l>The World doth know we live in dangerous times</l>
               <l>Let every good man then purge his owne crimes</l>
               <l>For my owne part I wiſh a generall Health</l>
               <l>To our moſt gracious King and Common-wealth</l>
               <l>If each true Proteſtant wiſh thus I hope</l>
               <l>They'le ſhunne the <hi>Devill</hi> as they ſlight the <hi>Pope.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
